Guide to the New-York Historical Society Financial Records 1837-2005 (bulk 1800s-1930s, 1980s-1993) NYHS-RG 24
New-York Historical Society
New-York Historical Society financial records
1837-2005 (bulk 1800s-1930s, 1980s-1993)
New-York Historical Society
NYHS-RG 24
18 Linear feet in 18 record cartons
Although the record group does not hold comprehensive records concerning N-YHS's financial history, there are several 19th century records (cash ledgers, mortgagee holdings documentation, bank books, etc.) that provide glimpses into N-YHS's early finances. Also there is extensive financial data (expenses, budgets, investments, etc.) for the late 1980s and early 1990s; though the timeframe is limited, it represents a period when N-YHS faced a severe fiscal crisis and so can provide insight into that pivotal moment in the organization's history. The record group also holds much information about many of N-YHS's special funds (e.g., Harper Fund) and the financial aspects of the Encyclopedia of New York City project.
Arrangement
The record group is organized in five series:
Series I. Investments, 1880s-1993
Series II. General Office Files, 1930s-2005
Series III. Account books, journals & ledgers, 1837-1927, 1958-1993
Series IV. Working files, 1988-1993
Series V. Encyclopedia of New York City Files, 1988-1991
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Most of the content of the record group was found in the archives at the time of the institutional archives project of 2015-16. The bulk of Series II was transfered to the archives by the Accounting & Finance Department in March 2020.
Scope and Contents
Although the record group does not hold comprehensive records concerning N-YHS's financial history, there are several 19th century records (cash ledgers, mortgagee holdings documentation, bank books, etc.) that provide glimpses into N-YHS's early finances. Also there is extensive financial data (expenses, budgets, investments, etc.) for the late 1980s and early 1990s; though the timeframe is limited, it represents a period when N-YHS faced a severe fiscal crisis and so can provide insight into that pivotal moment in the organization's history. The record group also holds much information about many of N-YHS's special funds (e.g., Harper Fund) and the financial aspects of the Encyclopedia of New York City project.
Related Materials
This finding aid relates to just one record group of the New-York Historical Society archives. Additional correspondence about N-YHS financial matters can be found throughout the General Correspondence record group (RG 2). Lists of expenses and investments, related resolutions, etc. can be found in the minutes of the Society and the Executive Committee (RG 1). Record groups for building construction (RG 3 and RG 4) have expense records for those projects. For information about the other record groups and for overall information about the archives, please see the overview Guide to the New-York Historical Society Archives (NYHS Archives).
Institutional investments.; Endowments -- Program-related investments.; Learned institutions and societies -- New York (State) -- New York -- Management.; Libraries and institutions -- New York (State) -- New York -- Management.; Museums -- New York (State) -- New York -- Management.; New York (N.Y.) -- History -- Societies, etc.; Financial records.; Mortgages.; Encyclopedia of New York City; New-York Historical Society -- Archives.
- Series I. Investments, 1880s-1993
  Scope and Contents
  The series holds some documents related to some of the mortgages, securities and other investments held by N-YHS from the 1880s to the 1940s and then in the early 1990s.
  Arrangement
  The series is organized in two subseries:
  Subseries I.A. Mortgage Investments, 1880s-1944
  Subseries I.B. Fiduciary Trust Reports, 1990-1993
  - Subseries I.A. Mortgage Investments, 1880s-1944
    The subseries holds correspondence and some insurance policies related to N-YHS's investment of its funds in mortgages in the late 19th and early 20th centuries.
    Related Materials
    Much of this documentation was taken from the General Correspondence (RG-2) files. It is likely that more such material remains in those files and should be referred to. Also, approvals, modifications, etc. of mortgages and other investments were made by N-YHS's Executive Committee through the late 1930s and the minute books of that Committee in the Management Committee records (RG-1) can be consulted. Those minutes have been digitized and can be viewed on-line.
    The series is arranged in chronological order. Files for the 1930s are further arranged by property/mortgagor, though not etailed in the finding aid.
    - Investments/mortgage documents, 1880s (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    - Investments/mortgage documents, 1890s (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - Insurance policies (24) on properties, 1860s-1890s (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    - Investments/mortgage documents, 1900-1908 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    - Investments/mortgage documents (2 folders), circa 1913-1928 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5-6)
      These documents were originally inside the front cover of the 1910-27 cash deposits journal (see below folder 33).
    - Investments/mortgage documents (26 folders), 1928-1944 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7-31)
  - Subseries I.B. Fiduciary Trust Reports, 1990-1993
    The subseries includes the monthly reports received by N-YHS from Fiduciary Trust International, the custodian of the organization's investments/securities holdings. These reports include schedules of investment at month-end, with portfolio characteristics and descriptions of activity in the accounts. Individual reports are present for the General Operating account and for the various segregated special purpose funds.
    The subseries is arranged by fund and then chronologically within each fund.
    - Bryan Principal Fund reports (4 folders), 1990 July-1992 June (Offsite-box 7, Folder 1-4)
    - Bryan Principal Fund (2 folders), 1992 July-1993 June (Offsite-box 9, Folder 11-12)
    - Harper Fund (4 folders), 1990 July-1992 June (Offsite-box 7, Folder 5-8)
    - Harper Fund (2 folders), 1992 July-1993 June (Offsite-box 10, Folder 1-2)
    - Matched Expense Account (2 folders), 1990 July-1992 June (Offsite-box 7, Folder 9-10)
    - Mellon Endowment Fund (4 folders), 1990 July-1992 June (Offsite-box 8, Folder 1-4)
    - Mellon Endowment Fund (2 folders), 1992 July-1993 June (Offsite-box 10, Folder 6-7)
    - Mellon Bridging Fund (2 folders), 1990 July-1992 June (Offsite-box 8, Folder 6-7)
    - General Operating Account (4 folders), 1990 July-1992 June (Offsite-box 8, Folder 7-10)
    - General Operating Account (2 folders), 1992 July-1993 June (Offsite-box 10, Folder 3-4)
    - DeWitt Wallace-Readers Digest Public Education Fund (4 folders), 1990 July-1992 June (Offsite-box 9, Folder 1-4)
    - DeWitt Wallace-Readers Digest Public Education Fund (2 folders), 1992 July-1993 June (Offsite-box 10, Folder 7-8)
    - DeWitt Wallace Endowment Fund (3 folders), 1991 February-1992 June (Offsite-box 9, Folder 5-7)
    - DeWitt Wallace Endowment Fund (2 folders), 1992 July-1993 June (Offsite-box 10, Folder 9-10)
    - Starr Foundation Endowment Fund (3 folders), 1991 April-1992 June (Offsite-box 9, Folder 8-10)
    - Starr Foundation Endowment Fund (2 folders), 1992 July-1993 June (Offsite-box 10, Folder 11-12)
    - Fiduciary Trust reports (16 folders), 1992 September-1993 December (Offsite-box 11, Folder 1-16)
      Includes the original packet of reports from Fiduciary Trust for the period 1992 September-1993 December. These are likely redundant of the above data through June 1993. Some of the packets have additionial documents, such as economic forecasts. At June 1993 there is an additional report from investment consultants, Colonial Consulting.
- Series II. General Office Files, 1930s-2005 (bulk 1970s-1990s)
  The series includes files compiled by the accounting and finance department primarily related to various endowment and memorial funds established by N-YHS over time. The files hold mostly photocopies of documents, but several files hold originals. Most of the files are somewhat slender, but files that hold a subtantial number of documents include those related to the Bryan Fund, Harper Fund, and Wilbur Fund. The files also hold information about some project grants, including those from the Mellon Foundation, NEH, and others, and audited financial statements from 1985-2004 with some gaps.
  The series is arranged roughly by topic with files on the special funds, which make up most of the series, preceding other topics.
  - General information about N-YHS endowment and memorial funds (14 folders), 1970s-1990s (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1-14)
  - Files on specific endowment and memorial funds (21 folders), 1970s-1990s (Offsite-box 3, Folder 15-35)
    These files include funds named for Waldron Phoenix Belknap (2 folders), Margaret L. Brown, Bryan Fund (6 folders), Levon Hein Chutjian, Thomas S. DaPonte, DeGroot, Edward Delafield, De Menil (2 folders), John DePeyster, Richard Varick Dey, Asher B. Durand, Louis Durr, Goelet, and Goldsmith.
  - Harper Fund (11 folders), 1950s-1990s (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1-11)
    These files have several original documents about the Fund dating from the 1950s.
  - Files on specific endowment and memorial funds (34 folders), 1970s-1990s (Offsite-box 4, Folder 12-44)
    Funds includes are those named for Harriman (3 folders), Hearst (3 folders), Hoffman, Ide, John Divine Jones, Leech, LeBoeuf, McKesson, Middledorf, Cornelia Post Mitchell, Doris R. Morton, Muhlenfels, Naval History Society, Orvis, Paltsits, Pell (3 folders), Phoenix, Ruth Samuel (2 folders), Sloan, Slocum, Sons of Rhode Island, Sotheby's, Starr, von Kienbush, Wallace, and Warner.
  - John J. Watson Fund (2 folders), 1940s-1950s (Offsite-box 4, Folder 45-46)
    These folders hold original 1940s-1950s documents, including correspondence between N-YHS curator Donald Shelley and Eliza Watson.
  - James B. Wilbur Fund, 1930s, 1990s (Offsite-box 4, Folder 47)
    These folder hold original documents from the 1930s re: the related case State of Vermont against Bankers Trust Company, et al.
  - Mellon Foundation Grants & Matching Funds (12 folders), 1970s-1990s (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1-12)
  - Other Funding Sources (21 folders), 1980s-circa 2005 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 13-33)
    Holds files on grants from NEH, NHPRC, state sources, and other grants for some programs and exhibitions.
  - Reinstatement of Property Tax Exemption (2 folders), 1972-1973 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1-2)
  - Financial Data for Attorney General, 1990s (Offsite-box 6, Folder 3)
  - Golden Loan, 1990s (Offsite-box 6, Folder 4)
  - Audited Financial Statements (8 folders), 1985-1995, 1997-2000, 2003-2004 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 17-24)
    The audited financials for 1994 are not here, but the 1994 year-end figures are in the 1995 report. 1996 and 2001-02 are not here. 1989 also has a copy of the Form 990; that Form is not in the files for any other year.
  - Various financial statements, 1983-1988 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 1)
    Informal balance sheets and income statements with various year to year comparisons for 1983-1988
- Series III. Account Books, Journals & Ledgers, 1837-1927, 1958-1993
  The series holds several cash account books and other similar accounting records for the 19th century and into the early 20th century. The container list identifies all of these and their date ranges. These early records are not comprehensive and there is a sizable mid-20th century gap in the series. More detailed are reports ranging from the mid 1980s to 1993, especially with respect to budget and actual expenses.
  The series is arranged roughly in chronological order and by type of accounting record.
  - Cash accounts/journals (3), 1837-1873 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 33)
  - "Blotter"/Cash deposits journal, 1910-1927 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 34)
    This volume held a great number of loose documents related to mortgages inside the front cover; these were moved to separate folders above (#5-6).
  - Checks, 1838-1839 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    A small number of endorsed checks.
  - Signed receipts for payments from N-YHS, 1837-1840 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
  - Librarian account book, 1848-1858 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
  - Accounts with W.W. Blennerhassett (binding), 1855-1856 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
  - Petty cash account books, 1871-1904 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
  - Bank books. General Account (2 folders), 1866-1907 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6-7)
  - Bank books. Special accounts (2 folders), 1898-1913 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8-9)
    Holds: Phoenix Fund (1898-1913); Durr Gallery Fund (1903-1913); New York Views Fund (1910-1913); Watson Binding Fund (1910-1913); and De Peyster Memorial Fund (1911-1913).
  - Bank book & pledge cards. Founders Fund, 1906-1913 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10)
  - Subscription receipt books, 1864-1870 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11)
    2 books: for a portrait of Luther Bradish (1864-65); for a portrait of Francis L. Hawks (1867-71).
  - Catalogue account/sales book, 1869-1876 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
  - Check book. Hudson-Fulton exhibition, 1909-1910 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 13)
  - Wage book (Payroll), 1916-1920 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 14)
  - Air conditioning & building renovation fund drive journal, 1961-1970 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 15)
  - Harper Fund ledgers (2), 1958-1985 (bulk 1970s-1983) (Offsite-box 2, Folder 16-17)
  - General ledger, 1982 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 5)
  - Investment register/ledger (2), 1985 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 6-7)
  - Trial balances, 1985 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 1)
  - Cash receipts journal, 1985 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 2)
    Provides daily detail of the sources of cash revenue for the calendar year.
  - Expense by account report and actual vs. budget reports for full year FY1987, 1986-1987 (Offsite-box 14)
  - Actual vs. Budget monthly reports (4 folders), 1989 October-1992 June (Offsite-box 13, Folder 2-5)
    Not all months are in the folders, but the reports include year-to-date figures. Most or all are focused on Library operations.
  - Expense vs. budget, general ledger trial, pre-audit financial statements for FY 1991 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 3)
  - Actual and budget reports for FY 1991, 1990-1991 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 6)
  - Actual and budget reports for FY 1992 (4 folders), 1991-1992 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 7-10)
  - Actual and budget reports for FY 1993 (3 folders), 1992-1993 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 11-13)
  - Deferred income reports, 1990-1992 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 14)
  - Monthly reports (36 folders), 1990 July-1993 June (Offsite-box 15, Folder 1-36)
    Monthly files with system-generated reports of various financial data.
- Series IV. Working Files, 1988-1993
  The series comprises various original files with detailed workpapers estimating expenses, etc., primarily for the early 1990s. These files also hold general information including chart of accounts, billing coding, staff/position lists, etc.
  The series holds a mix of original files that were found in no particular order.
  - Working files (2 folders), 1989-1990 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 15-16)
  - Working files (42 folders), 1988-1993 (Offsite-box 16)
- Series V. Encyclopedia of New York City Files, 1988-1991
  The series holds original administrative working files for the Encyclopedia project, including expense summaries, fundraising, budgets, reports, correspondence, advisory board notes, and NEH application and related materials.
  The original files remain in their original order as found in the archives, though there is no apparent order to them.
  - Encyclopedia of New York City Files (Box 1 of 2), 1988-1991 (Offsite-box 17)
  - Encyclopedia of New York City Files (Box 2 of 2), 1988-1991 (Offsite-box 18)